howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
this is a current episode currents are
shorter and less heavily produced than
our full-length episodes and generally
focus
on a single topic as always links to
books
articles and organizations mentioned are
available on the episode page at
jimrudshow.com that's jimrutshow.com
on this current episode my guest is
andrew taggart
we're going to start our conversation
around his medium post
the uninvited confession the new
confessional
great to have you here andrew uh it's
wonderful to be here jim
oh yeah i love these uh conversations we
start with a
starting point on in the current series
and then we go where it goes it'll be
fun to see where it goes
uh andrew calls himself a practical
philosopher
a non-dualist and an entrepreneur
now i wonder what the hell is a
non-dualist
in my life and i survived to live to
talk
to see the other day so i suspect that's
not it
uh and i'm also definitely a non-dualist
in the cartesian
sense and i suspect that's not it either
uh in in your
lingo what's an on duelist oh well we're
getting we're going pretty deep early
so nondualist refers to a number of
eastern traditions such as
zen buddhism and advice vendatta that
suggests
essentially that there is one reality
and we are that one reality so
so we have begun in the right place all
right that's a good play i guess it's a
good place to be still sounds a little
mystical to me but we'll dig into it a
little bit a little bit more about
uh andrew and this is from his website i
ask and seek to answer the most basic
questions of human existence with others
around the world
2009 i finished a phd left the academic
life and moved to new york city because
i thought the most basic question of how
to live
needed to be brought back into our
everyday lives
each day i philosophize with executive
entrepreneurs venture capitalists those
living in silicon valley and wall street
scandinavia and south america about the
nature of the good
life wow that's damn interesting you
know what who that reminded me of who
socrates yeah he didn't speak a venture
capitalist but
yeah well yeah he did but he just told
him to
you know get that get thyself to a
nunnery or whatever right
i hope you don't end up like him right
well it sounds like an interesting uh
life choice to be a
worldly philosopher yeah well it's it's
precisely what philosophy used to be
and so you're right to mention socrates
there are other figures we know of in
philosophical tradition all of whom
thought that
the most fundamental questions needed to
be asked with
other people with whom one was living in
order to help them
clarify their basic understandings of
what a good life is or
what reality is or why we're here so
indeed yeah so it's only i saw a tweet
you had
some months back about your mis your
misgivings about
i think it was analytic philosophy in
particular and i have similar misgivings
so i don't think that
i don't think that a current
understanding of philosophy as it's been
institutionalized is a very accurate
conception of what
the philosophical life was and really
ought to be
yeah in fact i you know i quote i
paraphrased wittgenstein original early
wittgenstein
and i basically say uh modern philosophy
is a long journey to nowhere right
yeah i mean i'm sure i'm sure there's i
like that
i'm sure there are some exceptions to
that rule but generally speaking
um both continental and analytic
philosophy
that is those undertaken in europe
and in anglo-america
seem to be involved in the
kinds of discourses that don't often
appeal to ordinary persons who are
really grappling with
meaning questions of meaning and purpose
and value
that's the the great trouble with the
institutionalization of philosophy as it
comes about in the 18th and 19th
centuries in germany
and afterward the united states so
suffice to say
what i'm up to is a fairly obvious thing
to do to
it we need to ask those questions and we
need to answer them
particularly at this moment in time and
philosophy has just been one of the
deepest
activities involved in those kinds of
inquiries
yep and even when i uh find it goes
nowhere nonetheless find it interesting
right so
in the last few weeks i've been digging
into heidegger oh for instance yeah
uh yeah and uh you know heidegger is a
little different because he also
uh talks about having to ground it in
everyday
life and all but he goes off to the wild
blue yonder and all kinds of crazy ass
but nonetheless it's stimulating
stimulating to think about and so i do
encourage people to read modern
philosophy
even at the end of the day you believe
it's uh you know
fireworks and jerking off mesa uh
basically
because it will make you think a little
bit and that's not a bad thing
no they're they're i'm enjoying this
conversation already
but um and there are philosophers who
might be
able to help you do more than jerk off
so there are
people like pierre doe who died in 2010
and he did argue very convincingly
things that ancient greek philosophy was
involved with
the questions of the good life there are
others like him as well even jm cooper
wrote a wonderful book called the
pursuits of wisdom where he discusses
epicureanism and stoicism
and platonism and so on in ways that i
think would be very
helpful for people living today yeah and
certainly there's been this very
interesting uh
neo-stoicism that's uh arisen of late
i'd happen to know a couple of the
figures in that field doesn't appeal to
me in the slightest but
uh uh you know i can see why uh
people would find it helpful and uh it
seems to be a good thing not a bad thing
just a matter of taste that it doesn't
appeal to my particular personality
i'm much more of an epicurean than i am
a stoicist i would say
i like the good life right uh you know i
don't
feel like uh you know sort of being
quiet and modest or whatever i'd like to
get out there and knock it around and
do little this and that and uh you know
have good time with my friends and
uh you know and think deeply right so
uh so yeah i would call it stylistically
uh a more of an epicurean than a than a
stoic
uh though uh you know philosophically i
can find
useful things in both traditions and
again those who listen to the show know
that
my one watch word which i apply to
everything the lens
is is it useful right i don't believe
anything a priori i tend to be skeptical
of ideologies and
uh certainly revealed religions but i
can use the lend is it useful on almost
anything
yeah well if we're talking about
philosophy as the loving pursuit of
wisdom or loving pursuit of living a
wise life then
i would argue that it couldn't be any
more useful exactly it's just
we forgot the more basic or
all-encompassing
use of the word usefulness i think
that's a good point
well let's dive into the focus of this
uh
current episode which is the medium
article you wrote the uninvited
confession
the new confessional and i'm going to
start off with a brief quote
uh over the years and most especially
during the coronavirus i've noticed an
unsettling trend people i barely know or
do not know it all will send me letters
written in a mode of a confession
completely out of the blue the writer
will not ask after me or mine nor at
least
he or she in any way include me and what
time was used to be termed a
conversation
instead the writer spills spilling guts
onto the page will speak
at me uh you know and then you go on to
talk about how this
uh is uh in your view very much related
to
uh i guess you might call it the uh
psychotherapeutic
culture uh what do you what do you have
to say about that
yeah it's a it's it's a it's a big it's
a very important and big
question i i want to say something first
by way of
by by way background so um
in 2017 uh i began to notice
that people were talking at great length
about work
and i think you've read a couple of my
pieces about the nature of work today
and so i i did have a kind of gestalt
shift or
a moment where things clicked and i
began to realize that joseph peeper who
was a
german philosopher writing in the 20th
century was on to something when he
spoke about
the nature of total work and the ways in
which human beings become
workers so i would call that the homo
economicus conception
now more recently i've been thinking
about
homo that is how it was possible
also for human beings to come to think
of themselves in deeply psychological
terms
so that's more or less the backdrop to
this particular piece
i mean there are a number of
sociologists writing in the 20th century
many of whom have begun to point to this
particular
topic i'm discussing today so philip
reef wrote a book in 1965 or so called
the triumph of therapeutic
and began to point to the fact that a
lot of people i noticed were starting to
become interested in
feeling good that was the good life you
might say was the life of feeling good
but more recently i think what's really
quite astonishing about
homo psychologicos is that we're seeing
a ramping up
of this interior psychological
dispensation or dimension in life
and so i'll just give you one particular
understanding so there's something i
call secular spirituality
that refers to going north of what ken
wilber calls the flatland
of our current culture but it's well
south
of transcendence so in that particular
no-man's land
you begin to notice people talking at
great length about their interior states
about certain sets of experiences they
have about certain
growth experiences and things like that
so i'm beginning to pick up on the ways
in which there is no such idea as a
there's a very little sense of a common
good or publicness
and there's a great turn toward interior
states
that are then going to be discussed
at a considerable length on instagram
via twitter and for me via email
yeah i certainly resonate with you
talking about there i grew up in a
working
working class area where uh nobody went
to therapy
right unless they were by court order or
you know a case of a real tragedy i
remember a mother whose young child
died in a swimming accident drowned
right i think she went to therapy
but therapy was not a thing right and i
went to college in massachusetts and
cambridge
and then i i also then moved back to
cambridge later and
started two companies and i came to
realize there was this huge industry of
what i came to call
recreational therapy uh and uh what the
right what are all these people doing
and i will
say to this day it has kind of astounded
me and
it's not not something i've ever really
uh you know got involved with uh
it just struck struck me as an oddity of
the modern world but as you point out
the
the discourse of uh what you might call
the depth psychologists in some ways
permeates our culture especially our
certainly our literary fiction a lot of
our movies a lot of our sitcoms etc
uh it really is uh you know quite a
fundamental part of the memetic
landscape
in fact i had a really interesting
cognitive science on
scientists on the show a couple of weeks
ago ep75
it was nick chater whose book the mind
is flat
does a really interesting scientific
demolition
of depth psychology and the idea that
there really is some true
depth uh to our personalities and that
you know in
rather what we're doing is reacting to
combination of perception and memory and
confabulation confabulating on the fly
right
it seems seems relatively convincing and
certainly uh
uh we know that uh freud and
you know his uh heirs and assigns like
young etc
uh aren't really scientists uh i would
call them closer to litterists you know
literary people
you know they write some write some
things that we resonate with right that
kind of strike us as yes that's about
what being a human is like in some sense
but when it actually puts it a
scientific test not so much
so anyway yeah that's my reaction to
this uh psychotherapeutic culture
and uh uh yeah it is uh
it is a really big part of the current
landscape
yeah so maybe i can provide a different
way of contextualizing why i actually
care about it now
i think two things tend to be lost or
foreclosed at this moment in time
one is a deep conception of the vita
contemplate
vita contemplativa that is the
contemplative life
and this was the life of contemplation
was extraordinarily important in ancient
greece going all the way through the
end of the early modern period in europe
it was really holding sway
so the life of contemplating ultimate
goods or ultimate things
was of fundamental importance and that's
not even remotely
part of the current landscape that we
see today but i think it's a fundamental
part of what it is to be human so that's
the first one i see that has been gone
by the wayside largely so
the second one though is was really
pointed out by a number of sociologists
throughout the course of the 20th
century and they were
they were trying to draw our attention
to the fact that
notions of the common good to use
aristotelian
to mystic language were dissolving
and so if we ask ourselves what has
happened instead to
to fill this void the void of the lack
of contemplation and the
lack of genuine public spiritedness a
genuine sense of the common good
i would suggest this very strange notion
of interiority
the long
micro inspection of certain interior
states
that will then be put in the form of
stories
and shared as if they were open secrets
they're open secrets on instagram but
then they become slightly more secretive
when it's actually in the confessional
mode in a one-on-one sense
so i can probably try to ground what i'm
saying in a very specific example
that i only allude to in that particular
article
a couple months ago i was introduced to
a man with whom i might
philosophize and i just said let's let's
call the man john
and so i said let's just have a chat
john and this is what i typically do
i'll just
have an ordinary conversation without
any kind of expectations
just to get a feel for him and for him
to get a feel for me
it was very striking about this
this this i guess monologue really was
that was precisely that but he was
monologuing
he he began really by telling me that he
had all these things going on and it
felt as if he was
i felt as though i was the therapist
right i was put
in the position of the therapist and he
was the one who was
the client or an alazand
and he was telling me three topics and
above all he was
suggesting that what really mattered to
him is that he didn't feel
understood or recognized and i could i
got the sense that this was a very well
grooved story
he told it over and over again over many
years i'd say the man was probably based
on the tone of his voice only maybe in
his mid 50s
early 60s and it was just
extraordinarily uncanny to me
and so when i asked him uh what what
would you like to know about me
since this is a ostensibly a
conversation
he said well the only thing i'd really
like to know is whether or not you heard
what i had to say
so that's what um therapy would call
mirroring so i mirrored it back to him
given and that's what was going on in
that particular tet attempt
but not without feeling a great sense of
disease about the whole thing
so it was a kind of click a moment when
things clicked
i saw this person was not alone i've had
conversations like this before
i've had exchanges like this before in
the past and i've wanted to see whether
there's
more to seeing these as particular signs
of the state of culture today at least
among those who are let's say elites
living in the east coast the united
states but i think also in other
places like san francisco and beyond
yeah i think uh i think that's an
interesting insight actually and
uh you know i would say uh definitely
uh that you know people as you say
they're looking at these what they think
are depths right they're dwelling on
uh neuro neurological phenomena
which you can there certainly are
interesting uh
uh neurological phenomena and they're
mistaking them for
something uh well they're real to say
that they're not real is not true
but the claim that they have deep
metaphysical significance right
and and you know this is what uh people
like john vervicky
talk about the meaning crisis when you
know nietzsche and the enlightenment
overthrew the traditional gods
uh rather than uh just dealing with that
and moving on
an awful lot of people continue to be
searching for surrogates and
various shallow forms of spirituality as
people call it
uh you know seem to be uh filling that
space
and the psychotherapeutic uh
hobby uh seems similar
yeah it i think
but let's let's even investigate what
what seems to be missing here
so those who have gotten very much
involved
in this hobby are missing a lot about
what it is to
to be involved in a good human life so
they're they're not cultivating the
virtues that aristotle would associate
with friendship or what he called philia
that is caring for another person for
his or her own sake
that's an extraordinarily important
feature of a good life i would say
but nor are they involved in let's say
volunteer activities
or what christians would call karitas
which is a forms of charity
uh ways of engaging other people who are
less off than we are that's another one
that's been
a part of the american tradition at
least during the 19th century surely
and and most important for me since i am
a zen buddhist
they're not as well as a philosopher
that kind of loop that they're involved
in is not enabling them to go
beyond the circle of their own
consciousness
so i azam buddhist doesn't care too much
about the content
of mentation that is whatever comes to
mind is whatever comes to mind
but the suggestion is that there
actually are forms of life
or ways of being that are beyond the
contents of your thoughts and feelings
and if you particularly devote your life
to looking at the contents of thoughts
and feelings over and over again then
you're really missing
um what we say you're missing the forest
for the trees
yeah i like that a lot uh the other
thing i liked a lot in your essay
is that you connected that perspective
to narcissism
and and you know there's been been quite
some time that
people have been pointing out that we
are developing a culture of narcissism
at a exceptionally high level and
you know this this phenomenon that
you're talking about strikes me as
uh an almost pure form of narcissism you
know that
you know my my little internal thingies
uh
uh you know are more important than you
know my relationships with my family or
my friends or my community or
or doing good works or uh one that i
notice has fallen off tremendously
uh is conviviality the idea of
you know really having uh deep
live personal entertainment with
friends rather than you know looking you
know going out to some canned concert
or uh or what have you so yeah i would
i would love to hear your your thoughts
on how uh the culture of narcissism
is uh interacting with these phenomena
right um i think it would be helpful to
put in context the the therapeutic
culture
and i'm still in the early stages of my
investigation so this is going to be
free willing here but let's consider the
what let's say carl pelenia writes in
his book the great transformation
as it pertains to the movement
over the course of capitalism from the
countryside to the city
so we can't we can't deny that
urbanization has been a remarkable force
at this moment in time as mega cities
have been created
and as young people continue to flock to
mega cities for
the purposes of career development and
making their way in the world and such
so that's at least one strand in the
argument so you have
deracinated individuals moving from
small town wisconsin where i grew up to
new york city
and it happens also in denmark where
i've spoken with people over the years
as it does in england as people are
moving to
london i mean the fact that you have the
self-possessive individual
on his or her own in the so-called
alienated
modern landscape is already suggestive
of someone who has broken ties to family
and to local communities
as part of the bargain for trying to
make his or her way in the world
so that's one strand that can help us
see how
narcissism could have arisen but then i
think we also have
what aristotle would have called friends
of utility
becoming more and more prominent today
in keeping with that
that which i just said that is friends
of utility
are those who are only useful to you
that narrow sense useful to you in a
professional sense useful
to you insofar as it allows you to
advance in the world
so i joke and say that linkedin right is
the place where you'd find
friendships of utility and nothing more
nothing less
so friendships are more and more not
understood
as the deep ties that bind us over the
course of decades but rather
as the kinds of incidental relationships
we have
with the view to our getting on in the
world at least if we are kind of
white-collar professionals or knowledge
workers in the bay area or in new york
city
and then david brooks wrote i'm really
exciting articles for here for your
listeners
but then david brooks wrote a really
nice piece in atlantic a few months ago
and he's talking about the erosion of
the of the of the family
or the nuclear family which he says was
really only prominent from after world
war
ii to the 1980s or so so if you begin to
actually look at any number of families
today
you'll see that some of some people are
incarcerated to be sure but other in
other cases you just have
young individuals trying to aspire to be
somebody
and more or less thinking of family in
the way that rousseau would have thought
about family
namely as those who are involved in kind
of a voluntary association
that no longer carries the kind of deep
long-standing obligations and duties
so you start to notice the ways in which
narcissism could arose it's i'm telling
something like right now a subtraction
story take away the sorts of of
fundamental connections we have with
others
and see what you're left with well
you're left with someone who more and
more is involved
in beginning to in a fairly neurotic way
look at or examine the contents of his
or her own consciousness
and then i would argue that the
workplace has also begun to
reveal a lot of these marks as well so
it's only in recent years that we've
heard talk about vulnerabilities
being shared and and facilitation
workshops being undertaken at various
tech firms
so it's also being encouraged for one to
be engaged in the kind of
looping around inquiry into one's own
states of consciousness
it's not surprising then and i don't
think i have all the strands
of the story woven together yet that you
begin to see more and more narcissistic
people emerging
in this context yeah indeed and you know
i'm involved with something called the
game b movement which is an attempt to
build a more
authentic uh way of being and one of the
things that we've talked about and i
think we put the date about 1925
is that the amount of personal
investment we have
we have in family and face-to-face
community
has declined since 1925 more or less
continuously
and what's taken its place has been the
market and government
and you know both of those are uh
essentially uh
abstract cold interfaces while the
family and the face-to-face community
are warm and complex and very high
dimensional
uh and that's just a very different way
to live
and uh part of our prescription of the
way forward is we call proto-b's which
is to develop
communities where we that take good care
of families because
families are the basis of everything
when we let our families go to hell
uh starting in the uh you know
world war ii but really accelerating in
the uh
late 60s and early 70s you know people
now become fractionated and no longer
connected in a matrix
of you know biological and emotional
obligation
and you know the way forward seems to us
to be to rebuild
communities such that the families at
the base and then the face-to-face
community
supports and helps the family create the
next generation of humans
who help make an even better community
which do an even better job of helping
support the family and
that's that's really what uh what comes
next should be about not even more
fractionation and more alienation of the
uh you know radically displaced
individual i agree
it's funny is that what you're
describing in some ways
tracks what al-stair mcintyre calls
revolutionary aristotelianism which is
which might strike some of your
listeners is a bit amusing
because he's really just referring to
more or less what you're talking about
face-to-face community centered on the
cultivation of moral intellectual
virtues
whose point and purpose is a human
flourishing and b
the common good we share together so
it's just a small scale community you
can find it in certain eco villages or
in certain tension communities at least
in principle not in practice
yeah and that's one of the reasons i
live in very remote virginia
uh you know the nearest grocery store is
an hour's drive over three mountain
ranges
but we have an intact community here
real people who can really rely upon
uh you know and you can get really get
to know over a period of years
and you know i you know i frankly can't
can't even imagine
being that uh nomad that i used to be
right who uh you know lived in this city
for a while in that city for a while
uh that that per that person was a uh
strangely shallow person
uh you know fortunately i have an upbeat
and optimistic personality so i never
uh you know think i ever really suffered
from it in the sense of feeling bad
but i think back at it it was you know
it was wide there were lots of
experiences on offer but it was only an
inch deep there wasn't any real
substance to it
yeah and i'd like to come back to
something we were saying just a moment
ago
and this is that what i also might be
lacking is an
understanding of of psychomoral
development
from let's say age 0 to 18 just to put
some arbitrary numbers on it
time was that i'm probably close to your
age than i am
to some of some of your listeners i'm 41
years old when
we still had chores to do when we were
when we were children
age 12 was not the age at which you
become dexterous at the piano age 12 was
the age of which you had some
you had a fair number of chores to do
around the house i didn't
particularly love these and nor am i
going to sing their praises
but being able to be embedded
in a household in household oikos the
household economy this
the way in which the household is
maintained is part of the cultivation of
characters aristotle would say
so even in 19th century as as american
families were much larger we had a
number of
younger younger people obviously working
on the farm
was it hard work to be sure i'm sure it
was quite painstaking work
but there was at least the
intergenerational
understanding of being able to fill
obligations to others
and the ability to actually cultivate
certain salient virtues
such as generosity or patience or
or even indeed conviviality and so
when you begin to when you begin to
create a different kind of human being
that is human being oriented toward
being the worker who's going to be
successful in the bay area or in new
york city
in the form of venture capitalism or
perhaps in the guise of startup
you're not actually getting that
fundamental period of time
the kind of human being that is born and
bred to engage
in acts of friendship and in community
engagements of the kind that we're
describing so
more or less uh the suggestion here is
that
narcissism of the kind we're seeing is a
residue
arising out of a series of
unacknowledged failures
that have occurred behind the scenes
yeah failures or moves i mean
uh you know i would call them failures
but society itself might not
right uh i mean we seem to be very happy
with
uh the breakdown of the uh
you know the traditional family you know
people seem to feel at some
level they're liberated so is that a
failure i would say it's a failure but
uh broader society doesn't seem to think
so
uh which is which is interesting you
know where does one get the perspective
to
to realize that having uh a society
where
you know 50 of kids are living
in uh single-parent households which is
not true quite yet for the whole country
but for some
sub-communities it's true i mean that
just is nuts from my perspective and yet
the world seems to think that's
fine and dandy i think we need to
distinguish i'm sympathetic to what you
say i think we need to
distinguish between a subjective
polling and some more robust conceptions
of living and faring well or eudaimonia
or the good life
if you so i'll give you one example
a number of people will get asked via a
pew poll
whether or not their work is fulfilling
or some such
and it depends on the poll and some will
say no one let's say yes but
by my lights this is a really poor
question on the whole
because i'm more or less skeptical of of
the whole system of gainful employment
that arises at the end of the 19th
century and really pick some steam
throughout the course of the 20th
century
i provide this as one example just to
illustrate the limitations
of polling when you have people the same
level of consciousness
as ken wilbur might say so instead
i would suggest that sure people are
let's say subjectively content with the
status quo
only in so far as in a fundamental way
they know no other right i mean the key
to living today
is in fact the the proliferation of
options in terms of a marketplace to be
sure
that's true but the lack of genuine
options
as it pertains to how to live in
a broader sense so we've basically
agreed
that the modern liberal state is
hegemonic
we've agreed that the market is
allegedly autonomous
we have agreed that human beings are
you know are disencumbered or
deracinated
individuals pursuing their own forms of
success
and subjective forms of utility or
happiness
i'm skeptical of the entire model as i
think you are when it comes to game view
as well
so polling is simply not going to do
much i think
when it comes to actually interrogating
what the nature of good life is
because of the extent to which people
have already for generations on end
bought into the current systems and no
basically no other yeah we call that in
the game b context game a malware
and uh you know frankly uh most of us
we're utterly saturated with it and our
growings up right
uh you know uh you know i was i'm quite
a bit older than you i'll be 67
this year and so i still had the
traditional uh working class
fairly solid family upbringing which uh
you know did me well but i was also
saturated in tv
and you know one of those guys one of
those uh
network tv uh era uh people where
uh you know this sort of dream world was
projected into our brains two or three
hours a day
and uh you know and it produced a
different kind of market
being a program to work hard so you can
buy
a fancy car and pick up chicks right uh
and it was psychologically well informed
though not as psychologically well
informed as
current internet advertising and it but
it knew how to press our buttons and
it knew how to build this mass man and
uh unfortunately that malware is just
one variety of it the current kind i
don't
understand as well since i did not come
up in that world uh but this world
that is no longer mass right i remember
you know people
uh you know younger people even folks
your age probably have a hard time
remembering a world when there were
basically four
three tv networks right and on any given
night
70 of american families were tuned to
one of the three
uh you know now we have an even more
interesting phenomena
of a crazed ubiquity of choice
roll your own reality essentially but
uh unfortunately as we've both been
talking about and
certainly game b underlines and i
believe your work does too
all the energy there is towards
fragmentation
and individuals not in the context of
the social
and you know that may be damn close to
the to the root of the problem
yes and i i and i i do think that if you
could
administer a truth certain to a number
of people who
um exhibit certain narcissistic
tendencies
and you begin to engage them in a
philosophical conversation
the kind that i tend to have daily such
that
they would play the role of the answer
and i would play the role of the
questioner
i think it wouldn't be hard to see
something
more more basic at play here
that's something we haven't touched upon
yet and that would be something like the
following i actually
am feeling dis-ease in the buddhist
sense some sense of
life being rather off or disconcerting
or not quite what it's supposed to be or
as i like to i like the
gloss the pali term dukkha meaning uh
things aren't spot on
really so that's what i think the person
would would say as much now the person
wouldn't confess as much the person
would actually be involved in speaking
the truth i think the other
important point that person would make
is effectively this i'm i'm actually
quite lonely
existentially so if you could begin from
that starting point namely
i'm actually discontent notwithstanding
the ways in which i proclaim in the
public
that i am content and i'm actually quite
lonely or lonesome notwithstanding the
fact that
i appear for all intents and purposes
among my cohort to be gregarious
otherwise
then you can begin to get some purchase
on how that person might be different
and
how collective life might be different
yeah i think that's that's correct i
mean certainly we know from
even from tracking polls that uh
you know loneliness is perceived
loneliness is definitely on the upswing
and the number of actual deep
friendships that people have a
surprising number of people now have
zero which is to my mind uh staggering
and
disastrous right uh people being a
friend that you could have a truly deep
conversation about something of great
sensitivity
right i like the old saying you know a
friend will help you move
a good friend will help you move a body
right
so so how many good friends do you have
i got about 10
right i think i'm damn lucky to have
that many right
uh but there are people who have zero
that would have to be a very strange way
to live
and then another another you know form
of what you're talking about that does
come through from the polling is the
famous question are we on the
is the country on the right track or the
wrong track
i just pulled it up uh the consensus on
real clear politics and this has been
uh consistent for years it's about 65
percent of people believe the country is
on the wrong
track and and that's you know kind of a
reification a lot of these things
there's
deep down inside people know this ain't
the right way to live this is not the
right way to raise
children you go to a restaurant you see
parents shutting the children up by
having
handing them an ipod you know when
they're an ipad when they're you know
five years old they go what the hell
uh you know this is an opportunity to
socialize children to bring them into
the conversation
uh to show them how to live and instead
the you know the parents want to
chat about their own little affairs they
want to shut the kid up by sticking
their face in a screen
you know at some level people know this
is wrong even if they can't articulate
it
i agree and what could also be said is
that
you can we can now provide a charitable
interpretation of why a fair number of
people let's say the east coast
tend to go to therapy that is because
if they don't have close friendships or
what aristotle called friendships or
virtue
if they don't have the kinds of
relationships with
their parents and siblings that enable
them to talk about matters of great
importance
if they are living in brooklyn
or in oakland
and if they are only working in ways
that allow them to
progress in their careers then there are
these big gaps
and those big gaps the ones being filled
by
you the the kind of purveyors of
cigaretty that is those who are able to
be substitutes for
what culture often or sane culture would
provide
so sane culture wouldn't need stop gap
measures
in the form of a professional class of
people we call therapists
yeah i think that's interesting it would
be actually i don't really get the data
but
uh do a calculation
uh of therapists per capita by county or
something probably the labor department
statistics might actually have
at least some rough and crude things and
see what that shows sure
i bet that would be interesting and then
correlate it with things like
uh population density number of people
who are
uh still working the land uh
etc uh i'm gonna do that just for fun
i i mean yeah yeah i mean i don't think
you have the poet wendell berry
living in rural kentucky uh going once
weekly
to a therapist nearby so
yeah i don't think so yeah wendell berry
i mean he's an amazing example
he actually was the commencement speaker
when my wife
graduated from college at a small
liberal arts college in kentucky and we
got the chance to chat with him
afterwards quite a
quite a fine human being that was a
zillion years ago
yeah yeah he's lovely so i've heard
it's interesting so what do we do
god damn it you know the pro the game b
answer is to literally start building on
the ground communities that exemplify
uh some of these ideas but of course at
least in the short run they don't really
scale if we did a great job maybe we can
build a hundred of them in the next
10 years and that would be home for
maybe 15 000 people
that of course is like spitting in the
ocean
what ideas do you have to you know help
people live more authentic
uh more grounded more real uh just
better lives the good life how can we do
that at scale
yeah i don't i i don't have great
proposals here but i have a starting
point
so this starting point would be a joke
it would be
never let a good crisis go to waste so i
think you'd need to begin with a certain
kind of collective crisis
you find in a number of different
traditions that and i found in my own
time of philosophizing with individuals
that it's usually
at a point at which a current way of
life
no longer makes sense and that's
understood very intuitively
very invisibly then you have the
beginning of a new possibility
so if you could begin to imagine a
number of people who
have been living according to the
dictates of
certain narcissistic narcissistic
tendencies and
more and more of them aren't just living
through coed
but something dare i say
more existentially potent than covid
then you have the beginning of the
possibility of what i call a collective
existential opening i think that's the
first step you really can't pull people
out of systems
as they are and expect that they will be
ready because they're not
they're not actually ripe for it you
don't just
for example have someone come and sit at
a sashim which is a zen buddhist
intensive meditation retreat for seven
days it's a very bad idea
you only begin with someone who has been
as buddhist would say
open to the great matter of life and
death
so this is the first part you're there's
you know you the the the joke might be
no scale without collective existential
opening
so yeah well we certainly we have that
in the game b world what we say
is that that we need ears to hear
and our hypothesis is the current
accelerated metacrisis of 2020 have at
least
increased the number of year years to
here by a factor of 10x
as opposed to uh january 1st and uh
you know we do intend to take advantage
of that and i i think that's uh that's a
good insight
yeah so the second point i would make is
that they're uh
in keeping with what you were just
pointing to
is there's a is that there's a kairos or
timing issue
i've noticed that people only tend to
open up
at a particular moment and the the
aperture
so to speak is only open so long before
they tend to return to
the ways that they had been living so
it's not just that you need to have as
jesus said
ears to hear you also need for people to
be
encountered right at the point at which
things don't make sense to them socrates
calls it opera
right the sense of confusion sense of
being turned about
if you can get those right that you can
have the beginning of a genuine
movement or a genuine shift in
consciousness
yeah i think i think that's right and
you know one you know just thinking
about this out loud as you're talking
yeah uh uh one that strikes me
as where the rubber meets the road for
millions of people
is the uh amazingly
chaotic state of public school education
right now
i mean this is kind of like business
travel
it strikes me that business travel will
never return anything like
it used to be i mean the the opportunity
to do it a different way people realize
do i really need to spend uh
you know three thousand dollars to go
out to california for two days for one
meeting
hell though right uh and i think this
crisis of public school education is
making clear to people
uh that the whole idea of the current
public school education is a
fairly much a nightmare of uh large
proportions
and uh opening around a better way
to raise your children including you
know organic education built right into
the way of life
may be an opening to millions of people
right now who really are
in crisis and and even the ones that
don't yet realize they're in crisis are
gonna realize it in a year when they
realize that most of their kids didn't
learn jack in the last 12 months
at least not uh uh you know not what
they thought they were supposed to learn
it's a good point of leverage i've as
you've already gathered i've been
interested in
our notions of work because i think
that's another very
low-hanging fruit so kovid certainly has
brought mass unemployment to millions of
americans
now a number of them are receiving
unemployment benefits right now
and a number of them will be funneled
back into the system
but it doesn't have to be that way
moreover a number of people are
learning new neologisms such as work
from home or working remotely
for a while that's their attention is
going to be sequestered they'll learn
that they don't have to live in the bay
area they can live in denver
or they can live somewhere around the
country so they're
they're starting to inquire but the
inquiry hasn't gone
very deep yet so if it were possible
actually to show that the ways we have
of working
are fundamentally untenable i would
argue
then we also have another leverage point
because our gainful employment system
is already hooked up to our public comp
or our public education system
right as it is as it's linked up to
other systems too so you really just
need to
put pressure on one system so that
through a level of thoughtfulness you
can begin to show people that actually
these are concatenated
they're they're linked to each other
right so a number of parents for example
i hear from are
are annoyed by the fact that they're
tired of having johnny or susie at home
because they're it's a dual income
household and so then now they need to
do babysitting and as you well know
public schooling apart from other things
is a is a way of
of having babysitting for eight hours a
day or so
so they're starting to feel the pinch
but they haven't really
analyzed yet the fact that it's also the
gainful employment system
of which they have been willing
participants that's allowing them to
actually not acknowledge the extent to
which they're feeling the pinch
yep and and i think the other key part
which take the next step from that
is most people can't synthesize the
solution
but they have but if they see one they
can recognize it right
uh you know for instance in our game b
proto-b concept
uh the idea of babysitting is actually
fully organic right it's part of the
society
uh and one of the areas that we i've
been researching in particular
uh for ideas for proto-b's are the
israeli kibbutz
right in the israeli kibbutz there there
was no arrangement you had to make for
daycare it was built into the social
operating system
that there were a group of folks whose
job it was to take care of kids while
their parents did other things whether
it was
arts or make love or what have you
and there was no hassle it didn't cost
anything
and it was just part of the social
operating system now there's some other
parts of how the kibbutz operated that i
would disagree with but i thought that
was
uh something that would very much
resonate particularly with young
millennial parents today
uh is that uh you know the the
nightmarish
difficulty of having your kids
watched over by the whole community
basically which
no longer exists would be a tremendous
liberating phenomena for the person
themselves and would be amazingly good
for the children as well and so
if we could build a social operating
system even at a small scale and be able
to show people come visit
see how the kids are just there are
essentially supervised by all the adults
together
uh and uh there are a few professionals
who make sure things don't spin out of
control
but you don't have to uh you know spend
uh 30 percent of your income on
uh on on child care that's nuts right
and and then which then allows you not
to have to have such an intense
pursuit of the almighty dollar and you
know but i think showing is going to be
uh real
important yes and on
on the other end of of life
the hope would be that we begin to
examine what it is to die
and to die the beautiful death for if
nothing else in this country we have
we have no sense of what it is to
actually die
a beautiful death to die well
so in the kind of community you're
describing presumably there would also
be
various understandings and ritualistic
practices
that would enable us to actually see
that yes this is
that so and so is coming to the end of
his life
let us find ways of honoring that end
and let us not cling to
that one let us not use massive amounts
of resources
to ensure that this one continues to
live a great
greater and greater impoverished last
phase of life
because we can't bear the possibility
that this one is going to go
ah yeah that's exactly right i did
happen to stumble across
your essay today on uh the uncomfortable
truths about the agent in modern society
and as someone who's getting at the
lower end of agent it definitely
resonates
uh you know and our society is so
up on the topic of death
we don't want to talk about it right and
uh
and you know this horrendous extension
of life i will say i'll get my
home family credit we're all goddamn
fatalists when the time comes pull the
plug we all have
uh you know advanced directives etc uh
we actually executed it with respect to
my father after he had a
weird accident uh at the age of 80 and
uh
you know the whole family got around and
basically kept him doped up and told
jokes for two days and then he was gone
right uh and uh and we did it with a
will and we had a good time about it we
still talk about how what a good time it
was was
as our father died right and uh and but
you know that's unusual in our society
he could have easily been
stuck on a ventilator for years
certainly for months what the hell
right uh and uh and we just do not we
don't think clearly about this
uh in fact one of my uh uh not entirely
joking uh ideas but a little you know
intentionally over the top
is that the social security
administration ought to authorize
anybody
75 or over to throw a going-away party
for themselves
and spend 25 thousand dollars doing so
uh provided that at midnight they take
the black pill
well joking
well there's a beautiful story uh as i
told you i live in the
southwest in albuquerque about edward
abbey edward abbey
uh was a staunch critic of
industrial capitalism uh and of
monkey wrench i read that book
a long time ago yeah it's a while it's a
wild book yeah
as well as desert solitaire which which
your listeners are probably more
familiar with
in any case when he was terminally ill
he was in the hospital this was the last
place he really wanted to be he was a
very cantankerous fellow
very risable fellow and and so his
friends
uh and true edward abby's spirit came to
the hospital
and sprung him from the hospital and
took him to
some unmarked location out in the desert
where he would have
found it quite beautiful and there he
died and they celebrated his death
excellent i hope some of my friends will
do that if when i need it though
hopefully i'll have the
uh the will and the foresight to do it
myself
no he probably wasn't quite as quite as
responsible as you and
all that on the other hand one of the
problems is of course is if you let it
go too far
particularly with dementia uh you know
you no longer have the capability
and that's why we have to confront this
stuff and be honest about it right
as i kid my daughter i say well if i
can't answer the question what's the
square root of 169 take me out back and
shoot me
right and uh
i sort of mean it right though obviously
we need a cleaner and better way to do
it
let me throw out a billion dollar
opportunity for any young entrepreneurs
out there
kavorkian clinics right you're going to
have to spend the first 10 years
in litigation and politics but
eventually
it'll be one of the biggest businesses
in america where people can go away with
style and with their friends around and
throwing the black pill party and the
whole deal death as a service
not a bad idea the reason i brought the
topic up
in keeping with how to raise children is
that in the philosophical tradition
these have all been questions of the
good life and so
i i just look around for the areas in
modern life
where we are not yet
open to examining things and in virtue
of not yet being open to examining them
it turns out that we are held fast
by our delusions and by our
unthoughtfulnesses
so this is why it's it's so remarkable
to me that people will
raise children so that they can become
workers and consumers and at
the at on the back end take care of
their grandparents
in such a way that suggests that they
couldn't possibly
let go of someone who is deteriorating
in myriad ways
we can't let go because we have no idea
what a good life was
we only know how to extend
what one philosopher calls bare life
of course unfortunately in the united
states there's awful also
just a lot of superstition you know
around things like
christianity uh that oh you know every
life is sacred we have to fight for
every minute of every life
you know that suicide is a mortal sin
and so we're also polluted with a lot of
that kind of thinking
well i mean i think what's i think
you're probably a card-carrying
secularist but
what can be said about about secularism
is that it actually imports
a lot of the assumptions from
christianity without actually owning up
to those assumptions
so it's certainly possible they have a
number of secular people who can't let
go of the grandparents but they have no
idea why they can't let go
of their grandparents yeah i think but
you know there's obviously our whole
tradition is deeply
uh infiltrated by the uh by two
threat as they say jerusalem and athens
right
plato and uh uh judeo-christianity
and both of them have are foundational
to who we are and
both of them have some good points and
both of them have some bad points if you
ever want to read a nightmare read
plato's republic right
uh personally i love socrates but uh
in that one not so much right or
essentially he's uh
describing something not too far from uh
the chinese
panopticon as uh as the way to run a
society
yeah by contrast
their socrates of what are referred to
as release or credit dialogues
i find in my own idealization to be
someone who
is really neat and appropriate for our
time and i think john viveki is
interested in socrates as well
i mean to say that here is someone who
is open to
enquiring with someone whether that
person be a statesman
or a craftsman about fundamental matters
of existence
without claiming that he knows what
wisdom is or
the way he knows what knowledge is he
knows what piety is or he knows what
virtue is or or what have you they go on
together
possibly with the view to converging on
mutual understanding but often with
with a view to actually come into their
state of confusion
together i i so if socrates were alive
today he'd be continually pointing to
the ways in which we
we are fusculatory when it comes to our
own sorts of confusions we
keep masking our basic confusions from
ourselves
so that would be another way of coming
back to the point you're asking about
how how to change things
so this is a third point that is you
start to
help people to unmask
the ways in which they are involved in
fundamental forms of misunderstanding
yeah i think that's uh that's bang on
well i'm going to end it right there i
think we've gone a little over our
normal time on these currents episodes
but this conversation was so
interesting and rich i think it was
great so
great to have you on andrew thanks very
much jim
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at modern
spacemusic.com
you